Guide to the François Gaston duc de Lévis papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
François-Gaston, duc de Lévis papers
1741-1780
1748-1773
GEN MSS 1135
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.21
(10 boxes)
Lévis, François-Gaston, duc de, 1719-1787
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Description and item-level list created by the donor, 1968. II. Defense of Provence During the War of the Austrian Succession, 1743-1770. III. French Campaign in Germany During the Seven Years' War, 1756-1763. IV. Hydraulic Engineering in Artois, 1741-1780. V. Court-Martial of Jean-Joseph Carrier de Montieu and Louis de Cassier de Bellegarde, 1770-1778.
Each series is arranged in order of document numbers assigned by the donor.
François-Gaston, duc de Lévis (1720-1787)
François-Gaston, duc de Lévis, French army officer and maréchal de France. As marquis de Lévis, he served in the War of the Polish Succession and the War of the Austrian Succession, succeeding Louis-Joseph de Montcalm as commander of the French army in North America in 1760. He was appointed governor of Artois in 1765, and maréchal de France in 1783, and created duc de Lévis in 1784.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hans P. Kraus, 1968.
Scope and Contents
Circa 500 manuscript and printed documents relating to military and political events in France, 1740s-1780s, and the military career of François-Gaston, duc de Lévis, including correspondence, diaries, maps, drawings, and other military and legal documents. Papers relate to Lévis's defense of Provence during the War of the Austrian Succession, 1748, and the ambassadorship of his cousin, Gaston Charles Pierre de Lévis, duc de Mirepoix, in London, 1749-1753; Lévis's participation in the French campaign in Germany during the Seven Years' War, 1762; construction of a canal between Saint-Omer and Aire, and other waterways in Artois, during Lévis's governorship of Artois, 1765-1780; and the court-martial of Jean-Joseph Carrier de Montieu and Louis de Cassier de Bellegarde for mismanagement of arms manufacture and inspection, for which Lévis served on the court, 1773.
Austrian Succession, War of, 1740-1748; Austrian Succession, War of, 1740-1748 -- Campaigns -- France; Courts-martial and courts of inquiry -- France; Hydraulic engineering -- France -- Artois; Seven Years' War, 1756-1763 -- Campaigns -- Germany; Generals -- France; Governors -- France; Artois (France) -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Artois (France) -- Maps; Artois (France) -- Politics and government -- 18th century; France -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; France -- Politics and government -- 1715-1774; France -- Politics and government -- 1774-1793; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- France; Diaries -- France -- 18th century; Technical drawings -- France -- 18th century; Maps (documents) -- France -- 18th century; Generals -- France -- 18th century; Governors -- France -- 18th century; Carrier de Montieu, Jean-Joseph; Cassier de Bellegarde, Louis de, 1723-; Lévis, François-Gaston, duc de, 1719-1787; Mirepoix, Gaston Charles Pierre de Lévis, duc de, 1699-1757
- Description and item-level list created by the donor, 1968; Series I
  - Description and list (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Defense of Provence During the War of the Austrian Succession, 1743-1770; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Documents: number 1 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 61)
  - Documents: numbers 2-3 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - Documents: number 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Documents: numbers 5-13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Documents: numbers 14-26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Documents: numbers 27-34 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Documents: numbers 35-46 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Documents: numbers 47-55 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Documents: numbers 56-62 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Documents: numbers 63-78 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Documents: numbers 79-80 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Documents: numbers 81-83 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Documents: number 84 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Documents: number 85 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 62)
  - Documents: number 86 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- French Campaign in Germany During the Seven Years' War, 1756-1763; Series III; 0.92; (4 boxes)
  - Documents (case 1): numbers 1-5, 7 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Documents (case 1): number 6 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 63)
  - Documents (case 1): number 8 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 64)
  - Documents (case 1): numbers 9-20 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Documents (case 1): number 21 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Documents (case 1): number 22 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 65)
  - Documents (case 1): number 23 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 66)
  - Documents (case 1): number 24 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 67)
  - Documents (case 1): number 25 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 68)
  - Documents (case 1): number 26 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 69)
  - Documents (case 1): numbers 27-40 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Documents (case 1): numbers 41-50 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Documents (case 1): numbers 51-62 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Documents (case 1): number 63 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 70)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): number 1 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 71)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 2-6 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): number 7 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 72)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): number 8 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 73)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): number 9 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 10-25 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 26-42 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 43-52 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 53-62 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 63-74 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 75-84 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 85-93 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 94-100 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 101-115 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 116-132 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 133-145 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 146-157 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 158-172 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 173-180 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 181-190 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 191-200 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 201-210 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Documents (cases 2-3): numbers 211-222 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Hydraulic Engineering in Artois, 1741-1780; Series IV; 0.66; (4 boxes)
  - Documents: number 1 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Documents: number 2 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Documents: number 3 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Documents: number 4 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Documents: numbers 5-6 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Documents: numbers 7-10 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Documents: numbers 11-15 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Documents: number 16 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 74)
  - Documents: unnumbered document (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Documents: number 17 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Documents: number 18 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 75)
  - Documents: number 19 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 76)
  - Documents: number 20 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 77)
  - Documents: number 20a (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 78)
  - Documents: numbers 21-21a (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Documents: number 22 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Documents: number 23 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 79)
  - Documents: number 24 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 80)
  - Documents: number 25 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 81)
  - Documents: number 26 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 82)
  - Documents: numbers 27-28 (Box 5, Folder 51)
- Court-Martial of Jean-Joseph Carrier de Montieu and Louis de Cassier de Bellegarde, 1770-1778; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Documents: numbers 1-3 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Documents: numbers 4-13 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Documents: number 14 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Documents: numbers 15-19 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Documents: numbers 20-24 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Documents: number 25 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 83)
  - Documents: numbers 26-28 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Documents: number 29 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 84)
  - Documents: numbers 30-36 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Documents: number 37 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 85)
  - Documents: numbers 38-40 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Documents: number 41 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 86)
  - Documents: numbers 42-50 (Box 6, Folder 60)